Guide to the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Division of Intercourse and Education
  - Subseries III.C: European Centre (Centre Européen)
    - Sub-subseries III.C.5: Cours, 1928-1939
      - Dupuis, Charles
        - La confederation germanique et la Societe des Nations, 1930 (Box 146)
        - La politique internationale de l'Europe, 1931 Nov 20-1932 Feb 5 (Box 147)
        - La politique et la droit
          - 1933 Mar 3-1933 May 19 (Box 147)
          - 1934 Mar 7-1934 May 23 (Box 148)
          - 1936 Mar 4-1936 Apr 1 (Box 148)
      - Dupuis, Rene
        - Droit du politique contemporaine, 1936 Nov 18-1936 Dec 2 (Box 148)
        - Les nouvelles formes de l'etat totalitaire, 1937 Nov 17-1937 Dec 15 (Box 148)
        - La politique exterieure des etats totalitaires, 1938 Nov 16-1938 Dec 14 (Box 148)
      - Escarra, Prof. Jean. La Societe des Nations et le conflit Sino-Japonais. Paris, France, 1933 Jan 12-1934 Feb 23 (Box 149)
      - Francqueville, 1928-1929 (Box 149)
      - Gidel
        - L'idée de souveraineté, 1929 (Box 149)
        - Droit maritime international, 1935 Nov 12-1935 Dec 10 (Box 149)
        - Les canaux maritimes en le droit international, 1939 Apr 26-1939 May 10 (Box 149)
      - Guyot, Raymond. Histoire diplomatique (1815-1870)
        - 1930 Nov 18-1931 April 14 (Box 150)
        - 1931 April 21-June 2 (Box 151)
      - Hamel. Questions bancaires internationales, 1927 (Box 151)
      - Hoijer. Le blocus economique, 1938 Feb 18-1938 Mar 18 (Box 151)
      - Jeze. Finances internationales, 1936 Mar 4-1936 May 20 (Box 151)
      - Le Fur
        - Philosophie du droit des gens
          - 1931 Feb 11-1931 Apr 29 (Box 152)
          - 1931 Nov 18-1932 Jan 27 (Box 152)
          - 1934 December 12-1935 Feb 27 (Box 152)
        - Les principes du droit international moderne, 1937 Nov 19-1938 Feb 11 (Box 153)
      - Maurain, Jean. Histoire diplomatique (1871-1914), 1933 Nov 10-1934 May 18
        - 1933 Nov 10-1934 Jan 12 (Box 153)
        - 1934 Feb 2-May 18 (Box 153)
      - Mirkine-Guetzévitch
        - Les traits internationaux de l'Europe orientale, 1929 (Box 154)
        - Le droit constitutionnel dans ses rapports avec le droit international publique
          - 1932 Mar 4-1932 Apr 22 (Box 155)
          - 1933 Mar 3-1933 May 26 (Box 155)
          - 1934 Mar 2-1934 May 18 (Box 155)
          - 1935 Mar 15-1935 May 29 (Box 155)
        - Droit constitutionnel international
          - 1936 Mar 13-1936 May 29 (Box 156)
          - 1937 Mar 5-1937 May 21 (Box 156)
        - Droit constitutionnel et droit international
          - 1938 Apr 29-1938 May 27 (Box 156)
          - 1939 Apr 21-1939 May 19 (Box 156)
      - Muzzey, David. Problemes actuels de la politique interieure et exterieure aux Etats-Unis, 1937 Feb 19-1937 Mar 12 (Box 156)
      - Potter, Pitmann B. Doctrines americaines de droit internationale, 1936 May 8-1936 May 29 (Box 156)
      - Ray, M. Jean. La position, l'oeuvre et la politique du Japon en Mandchourie, 1933 Mar 9-1933 May 4 (Box 157)
      - Renouvin
        - Histoire diplomatique de 1815 à 1914 1927-1928
          - 1937 Dec 6-1938 March27 (Box 157)
          - 1938 April 17-June 5 (Box 158)
          - 1928 Nov-Dec (Box 158)
          - 1929 (Box 158)
        - Histoire diplomatique (1870-1914), 1931 Nov 17-1932 Apr 12 (Box 159)
        - Histoire diplomatique de l'Europe avant 1914 1936 Mar 3-1936 May 26 (Box 160)
        - Histoire diplomatique de l'Europe (1848-1890), 1936 Nov 17-1937 May 25 (Box 160)
        - Histoire diplomatique de l'Europe (1890-1919), 1937 Nov 16-1938 May 24 (Box 161)
        - Histoire diplomatique de l'Europe (1848-1890), 1938 Nov 22-1939 May 23
          - 1938 Nov 22-1939 Jan 10 (Box 161)
          - 1939 Jan 17-May 23 (Box 162)
      - Scelle. Le fonctionnement de la Societe des Nations, 1936 Apr 29-1936 May 27 (Box 162)
      - Serruys, 1929 (Box 162)
      - Siegfried. L'education civique et l'enseignement de la science politique dans les democraties modernes, 1938 Mar 8-1938 Apr 5 (Box 162)
      - Stuart, Graham. Diplomatie Americaine, 1934 Nov 13-1934 Dec 6 (Box 162)
      - Tibal, Andre
        - 1927-1928
          - 1927 Nov 16-1928 Feb 29 (Box 163)
          - 1928 March7-June 6 (Box 164)
        - 1928-1929
          - 1928 Nov 14-Dec 5 (Box 164)
          - 1928 Dec 12-1929 Feb 27 (Box 165)
          - 1929 April 24-June 12 (Box 166)
        - Histoire des institutions evolution constitutionnelle et parlementaire des etats européens depuis 1918 1930 Nov 19-1931 Jun 10
          - 1930 Nov 19-Dec 12 (Box 166)
          - 1930 Dec 17-1931 May 6 (Box 167)
          - 1931 June 3-June 10 (Box 168)
        - Le desarmement (1919-1932), 1931 Nov 6-1932 Jun 10
          - 1931 Nov 6-1932 March11 (Box 168)
          - 1932 April 8-June 10 (Box 169)
        - Histoire diplomatique contemporaine (1919-1924)
          - 1931 Nov 18-1932 Jan 27 (Box 169)
          - 1932 Feb 3-June 8 (Box 170)
          - 1932 Nov 9-Dec 7 (Box 170)
          - 1932 Dec 14-1933 May 24 (Box 171)
        - Histoire diplomatique contemporaine (1925-1932), 1933-1934
          - 1933 Nov 8-Nov 29 (Box 171)
          - 1933 Dec 6-1934 May 9 (Box 172)
          - 1934 May 16-May 30 (Box 173)
        - Histoire diplomatique contemporaine (1914-1924), 1934 Nov 7-1935 May 28 (Box 173)
        - Histoire diplomatique contemporaine (1926-1934), 1935 Nov 12-1936 May 26 (Box 174)
        - Histoire diplomatique de l'Europe (1918-1936), 1936 Nov 18-1937 May 26
          - 1936 Nov 18-1937 Jan 20 (Box 174)
          - 1937 Jan 27-May 26 (Box 175)
        - Histoire diplomatique de l'Europe (1919-1934), 1937 Nov 17-1938 May 25 (Box 175)
        - Histoire diplomatique de l'Europe (1919-1925), 1938 Nov 16-1939 May 31 (Box 176)
      - Truchy
        - La reconstruction economique de l'Europe
          - 1931 Nov 20-1932 Feb 5 (Box 176)
          - 1932 Nov 18-1933 Jan 27 (Box 177)
          - 1935 Jan 4-Mar 8 (Box 177)
        - Les conditions generales du redressement economiques, 1933 Nov 10-1934 Jan 19
          - 1933 Nov 10-Dec 8 (Box 177)
          - 1933 Dec 15-1934 Jan 19 (Box 177)
        - Reconstruction economique internationale
          - 1935 Nov 15-1935 Dec 13 (Box 178)
          - 1936 Nov 20-1936 Dec 23 (Box 178)
      - Whitton, John B.
        - La doctrine de Monroe, 1932 Mar 4-1932 May 25 (Box 178)
        - Diplomatie americaine, 1934 Dec 11-1935 Jan 22 (Box 178)
  - Subseries III.D: London Office, 1935-1947
    (8 boxes)
    In 1936 an Advisory Council was created to bring the work of the Endowment into closer contact with individuals and institutions in Great Britain with aims similar to those of the Endowment. The London Office, organized under the general supervision of the Directeur-Adjoint in Paris, was guided by this Council. (Source: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace: Summary of Organization and Work. Washington DC: CEIP, 1941 p28.)
    - 1935 Dec-1937 June (Box 179)
    - 1937 July -1938 Aug (Box 180)
    - 1938 Sept-1939 May (Box 181)
    - 1939 June -1947 (Box 182)
    - American Library and Information Service, 1939 (Box 182)
    - American Studies in British Universities, 1937-1939
      - 1937 (Box 182)
      - 1938-1939 (Box 183)
    - American Studies in Higher Education Conference (Dunford House, 3-4 June 1939), 1937-1939 (Box 183)
    - Derry, T.K., 1938 (Box 183)
    - Dunford House, 1925 1927-1947
      - 19251927-1933 (Box 183)
      - 1935-1945 (Box 184)
      - 1946-1947 (Box 185)
    - English Speaking Union, 1937-1939 (Box 185)
    - Fuess, Claude, 1937-1938 (Box 185)
    - Institutt for Samfunnsfosking og Arbeidslære, 1939 (Box 185)
    - International Conference on Economic and Monetary Problems (Chatham House), 1935-1937 (Box 185)
    - International Relations Clubs (Box 185)
    - Royal Institute of International Affairs, 1933 1938 (Box 185)
    - Scott, Joseph, 1937-1938 (Box 185)
    - Sulgrave Institution, 1922-1926 1937 (Box 186)
    - University College of Wales, Aboryswyth Vacation School of American History, 1938 (Box 186)
- Series IV: Division of International Law
  (150 volumes, 9 boxes)
  The Trustees of the Endowment formed the Division of International Law to: (1) to aid in the development of international law and its acceptance among nations; (2) establish a better understanding of international rights and duties and a sense of international justice among the countries throughout the world; and (3) promote a general acceptance of peaceable methods in the settlement of international disputes.
  The Division devoted its efforts in three principal areas: facilitating the study and improving the teaching of international law and related subjects; furthering the development of international law and restating its rules in a more unified and systematic way; and improving the documentation of international law through a publication program resulting in the production of some 200 volumes.
  The Division helped found and support an Academy of International Law, which opened in 1923 provided financial and administrative support to six conferences of teachers of international law between 1914 and 1941 sponsored a series of eight summer sessions on international law to which it invited teachers from smaller colleges and prospective teachers who expected to begin their academic careers in small colleges; and awarded a series of fellowships in international law for the purpose of increasing the number of qualified scholars in the field.
  Soon after its formation, the Division of International Law entered into a cooperative arrangement with the Institut de Droit International. Through this arrangement the Institut created an advisory committee to counsel the Division, and in turn, the Institut for many years received financial assistance from the Endowment to encourage attendance at its sessions and aid in the publication of Annuaires. The Division also helped establish the American Institute of International Law in 1915 cooperated with and supported Harvard Research in International Law; financially assisted other societies of international law including the Grotius Society of London, the Société de Législation Comparée of Paris, the Association Yougoslave de Droit International of Belgrade, the Istituto Italiano di Diritto Internazionale of Rome, and the International Law Association; cooperated with governmental and non-governmental organizations including the Department of State of the U.S, the Neutrality Board of the United States, the Pan American Union, the Advisory Board of Jurists at the Hague, the Inter-American Commission of Jurists created by the International Conferences of American States, and the Permanent Court of International Justice; and lent technical and other specialized assistance to the work of several assemblies and conferences, including the American Commission to Negotiate Peace at Paris (1919), the Washington Conference on the Limitation of Armament (1921-1922), and several of the Pan American Scientific Congresses.
  The Division gave financial assistance to several international law books and journals by purchasing copies and distributing them to libraries and other interested institutions. The Division also had its own extensive publication program issuing collections of international documents, reports of tribunals, treatises, pamphlets and monographs on particular topics, and the series the "Classics of International Law," the publication of which the Endowment took over from the Carnegie Institution. (Source: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace: Summary of Organization and Work. Washington DC: CEIP, 1941 pp31-45.)
  Series IV. is organized into the following subseries:
  A. General
  B. Classics of International Law
  C. Conferences
  D. Fellowships
  E. Meetings
  F. Promotion
  G. Reports and publications
  H. Repor on Teaching of International Law
  - Subseries IV.A: General
    (92 vols, 5 boxes)
    The volumes for 1910-1935 are indexed unless otherwise noted. (Indices are available in RBML. Electronic versions of the indices are in preparation.)
    - 1910-1911 (Volume 252-253)
    - 1912 (Volume 254-256)
    - 1913 (Volume 257-258)
    - 1914 (Volume 259-261)
    - 1915 (Volume 262-263)
    - 1916 (Volume 264-265)
    - 1917 (Volume 266-268)
    - 1918 (Volume 269-272)
    - 1919 (Volume 273-276)
    - 1920 (Volume 277-280)
    - 1921 (Volume 281-284)
    - 1922 (Volume 285-288)
    - 1922-1925 (Box 186)
      (Not included in index.)
    - 1923 (Volume 289-293)
    - 1924 (Volume 294-299)
    - 1925 (Volume 300-303)
    - 1926 (Volume 304-306)
    - 1927 (Volume 307-309)
    - 1928 (Volume 310-312)
    - 1929 (Volume 313-315)
    - 1930 (Volume 316-319)
    - 1931 (Volume 320-323)
    - 1932 (Volume 324-330)
    - 1933 (Volume 331-335)
    - 1934 (Volume 336-338)
    - 1935 (Volume 339-343)
    - 1936
      These papers were intended to be bound for a 1936 volume. No index is included.
      - Jan-Feb (Box 186)
      - March-May (Box 187)
      - June -Sept (Box 188)
      - Oct-Dec (Box 189)
    - 1937-1940 (Box 189)
    - 1941-1947 (Box 190)
  - Subseries IV.B: Classics of International Law, 1910-1926
    (8 vols)
    - 1906-1916
      - A-B (Volume 344)
      - C-L (Volume 345)
      - M-Z (Volume 346)
    - 1917 (Volume 347)
    - 1918 (Volume 348)
    - 1919-1921 (Volume 349)
    - 1922-1923 (Volume 350)
    - 1924-1926 (Volume 351)
  - Subseries IV.C: Conferences
    ( 2 vols)
    - Third Conference of Teachers of International law, 1928 (Volume 398)
    - Fourth Conference of Teachers of International Law, 1929 (Volume 399)
  - Subseries IV.D: Fellowships, 1925-1935
    (42 volumes, 12 boxes)
    Dates represent academic years. The volumes in this subseries are indexed. (Indices are available in RBML. Electronic versions of the indices are in preparation.)
    - 1925-1926 (Volume 352-353)
    - 1926-1927 (Volume 354-357)
    - 1927-1928 (Volume 358-362)
    - 1928-1929 (Volume 363-365)
    - 1929-1930 (Volume 366-369)
    - 1930-1931 (Volume 370-373)
    - 1931-1932 (Volume 374-377)
      (Vol 75 (1679-2511) missing.)
      - 1932-1933 (Volume 378-381)
      - 1933-1934 (Volume 382-387)
      - 1934-1935 (Volume 388-393)
      - Fellows theses:
        - Alexander, Norman. Rights of aliens in the United States. 1925 (Box 191)
        - Brennan, Helen
          - Current international law…September 15, 1921-May 15, 1922. 1922 (Box 191)
          - The treatise on reprisals of Bartolus of Sassoferrato. 1924 (Box 191)
        - Buss, Claude A. (Box 191)
        - The constitutional convention of Pennsylvania, 1837. 1924 (Box 191)
        - The events leading to the Mexican War. 1925 (Box 191)
        - The Genesis of so-called traditional isolation as expressed in writings of the Fathers. 1925 (Box 191)
        - Studies in diplomacy. Benjamin Franklin and John Hay. 1925 (Box 191)
        - Carlston, Kenneth Smith. The nullity of international arbitral awards. 1933 (Box 191)
        - Christensen, A.N. A study of the plebiscites held under the provisions of the treaties of Versailles and Saint Germain. 1930 (Box 192)
        - Cutler, John Ward. The treatment of foreigners in relation to the draft convention and conference of 1929. 1933 (Box 192)
        - Dillard, Hardy C. The principle of estoppel, with particular reference to its application by international tribunals. 1931 (Box 192)
        - Dimitroff, Deltcho. La Bulgarie, le probleme de la Thrace et l'access a la mer Egee… 1934 (Box 192)
        - Dunn, Frederick Sherwood
          - International law and private property rights in Mexico. 1927 (Box 192)
          - The new international status of the British Dominions. The Development of the legislative process in international law. 1927 (Box 192)
        - Gano, Barbara A. International protection of women and children. (With this is bound her International ice patrol.) 1934 (Box 192)
        - Gantenbein, James W.
          - The doctrine of continuous voyage particularly as applied to contraband and blockade. 1928 (Box 192)
          - The doctrine of ultimate destination: the British applications during the world war and the American protests… 1926 (Box 192)
          - The doctrine of ultimate destination: and historical survey to the outbreak of the world war… 1925 (Box 192)
          - The doctrine of ultimate destination and the future. 1925 (Box 193)
          - The "Petergoff" as a precedent for applying the doctrine of ultimate destination to conditional contraband. 1928 (Box 193)
        - Garfield, Wadsworth
          - Clipping thesis. 1925 (Box 193)
          - Miscellaneous articles. 1926 (Box 193)
        - Geyerman, Fred J.
          - Guarantee treaties. Their operation and interpretation. 1924 (Box 193)
          - International Law. 1922 (Box 193)
          - Shall Congress ratify the Colombian treatyÀ 1924 (Box 193)
        - Gosnell, Cullen Bryant. Compulsory arbitration of international differences… 1927 154 p. Carbon type script. (Box 193)
        - Gray, Welles Alexander.
          - The anti-Japanese boycott, 1925 (Box 193)
          - The international pacific sanction. 1926 (Box 193)
          - Municipal indebtedness in Minnesota. 1924 (Box 193)
        - Hessler, William H.
          - The Contribution of the United States to the judicial settlement of international disputes. 1926 (Box 194)
          - International organization and National State Sovereignty. 1926 (Box 194)
        - Houghton, Nealie Doyle. De facto governments: a study in international law and American policy. 1927 (Box 194)
        - Hsu, Tun Chan. The council of the League of Nations. 1930 (Box 194)
        - Jaeger, H.E. International law as a part of the municipal law of the U.S. The circumstances leading to the promulgation of the Monroe Doctrine. The law of Angary in international law. 1926 (Box 194)
        - Jaeger, Walter H. Introduction a une etude sur les rapports entre le droit international public et le droit public francais. 1927 (Box 194)
        - Krylov, S. B. Materials for the history of the United Nations. 1949 (Box 195)
        - Laing, Lionel H. Merchant shipping legislation (and other papers) submitted with application for fellowship. 1934 (Box 195)
        - Lipovanu, Ioan. L'apatridie… 1935 (Box 195)
        - Liu, Shih Shun. Extraterritoriality: its rise and its decline. 1924 (Box 195)
        - Lotz, Walther. "Die deutsche Staatsfinanz-Wirthchaft in Kriege" (trans. By Prof. W. Alison Phillips) 1924 (Box 195)
        - Lycan, Gilbert L. The place of neutrality in the present international society (and other papers). 1935 (Box 196)
        - MacKenzie, N.A.M. Miscellaneous Articles. 1926 (Box 196)
        - Marshall, Charles Burton. Problems in the adjudication of international claims: the arbitrations between the United States and Mexico under the conventions of September 8 and 10, 1923. 1935 (Box 196)
        - Micheles, Vera. Dual nationality and absence of nationality during the World War and after. 1926 (Box 196)
        - Moore, Roger D.
          - International law and the Ruhr. 1926 (Box 196)
          - The friendship of the English-speaking peoples. 1924 (Box 196)
          - Aspects of international life. (clipping thesis). 1926. (Box 197)
        - Münch, Friedrich. The delimitation of waters under national control. 1931 (Box 197)
        - Noble, George Bernard. International attitudes. 1925 (Box 197)
        - Ogdon, Montell. Influences of the concept of the independence and equality of states upon the law of diplomatic immunity. 1934 (Box 197)
        - Pasching, Walter. The rules contained in the "General principals of law recognized by civilized nations"… 1932 (Box 197)
        - Randolph, Bessie Carter. Regional understandings. 1926 (Box 198)
        - Raphael, Maxwell I.
          - International law and the French revolution, a preliminary bibliography. 1924 (Box 198)
          - The right of separate action in the enforcement of the treaty of Versailles. 1924 (Box 198)
        - Reiff, Henry. Memorandum on an inquiry onto the legal status of government ships employed in commerce. Consent as a juristic basis of international law. An inquiry into the enforcement of certain multi-lateral conventions by the United States. 1927 (Box 198)
        - Ronhovde, Andreas G. Discrimination in the treatment of aliens. 1934 (Box 198)
        - Sewell, Franklin Clarence. The nature and interpretation of treaties. 1932. (Box 198)
        - Shiman, Russell Gardner.
          - The relations of the United States with France during the peace negotiations of 1782. The origin and birth of the British labour party. The establishment of the gold exchange standard in the Philippines. 1927 (Box 199)
          - The United States and the conference of Algesiras. 1927 (Box 199)
        - Shipman, Gordon D. The inequality of states in international organization. 1932 (Box 199)
        - Stone, Ivan M. The relation of petroleum to American foreign policy. 1926 (Box 199)
        - Suzuki, Kazumi. The Responsibility of States for Acts of Political Parties. 1935 (Box 199)
        - Thormodsgard, Olaf H. Constitutional law-search and seizure-self incrimination. 1926 (Box 199)
        - Thormodsgard, Olaf H. and Moore, Roger D. Recognition in international law. 1926 (Box 199)
        - Timm, Charles August. The Diplomatic relations between Brazil and the United States. 1927 (Box 199)
        - Toelle, J.H. (Box 200)
          - The Court of claims; its jurisdiction and principal decision bearing on international law. 1925 (Box 200)
          - The rights of the United States in the post-war settlement. 1925 (Box 200)
          - The Status of the territory of Memel. 1925 (Box 200)
        - Trautwein, Dorothy A.
          - Custom and present day international law. 1930 (Box 200)
          - The status of diplomatic agents engaged in trade or other unofficial activities. 1930 (Box 200)
        - Vallindas, Peter. Uniformity of interpretation of the international treaties in private international law. 1932 (Box 200)
        - Walker, Adolf. Comment on Article 15 of the Convention on Treaties adopted by the 6th International Conference of American States, Havana, 1928. 1930 (Box 200)
        - Whiteman, Marjorie. In the moot court of appeal. Action for specific performance of contract. 1928 (Box 200)
        - Wilcox, Francis Orlando. Induced ratification to international conventions. 184 p. 1934 (Box 200)
        - Williams, Edward B. The convention on treaties, Havana, 1928. Article II. 1931 (Box 200)
        - Wilson, Robert R.
          - Bartolus' theory of an international system. 1923 (Box 200)
          - Foreign consulships under the confederate states of America. 1924 (Box 200)
          - The progress of international arbitrations since the world war. 1925 (Box 200)
        - Wynne, Edward C. Japanese Feudalism. 1925 (Box 200)
        - Yokota, K. The league of Nations in its Relation to International Law. 1928 (Box 201)
  - Subseries IV.E: Meetings, 1928-1947
    (1 box, 2 volumes)
    - 1928-1929 1940-1947 (Box 202)
    - Institute of International Law Meeting, 1929 (Volume 400-401)
  - Subseries IV.F: Promotion, 1923-1949
    The fellowships file includes summaries of applications for the years 1935-1936 and 1936-1937.
    - Fellowships, 1923 1926 1935-1937 (Box 202)
    - Teaching, 1937-1948 (Box 202)
    - Inter-American Academy of Comparative and International Law, 1937-1949 (Box 203)
  - Subseries IV.G: Reports and publications, 1936-1948 undated
    (3 folders)
    - This subseries includes programs, brochures, reports, and conference proceedings created as a result of or related to activities of the Division of International Law. (Box 204)
  - Subseries IV.H: Report on Teaching of International Law, 1913-1921
    (4 volumes)